<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocappendix="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<?rfc comments="no" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="exp" docName="draft-muks-dns-filtering-05" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="3" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.31.0 -->
  <front>
    <title>EDNS options for filtering information</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-muks-dns-filtering-05"/>
    <author fullname="Mukund Sivaraman" initials="M." surname="Sivaraman">
      <organization>Banu Systems Private Limited</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>6001 Beach Road, #19-09, Golden Mile Tower</street>
          <code>199589</code>
          <country>SG</country>
        </postal>
        <email>muks@banu.com</email>
        <uri>https://banu.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date/>
    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Operations and Management Area</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <!-- <keyword>dns</keyword> -->

    <abstract>

      <t>This memo documents EDNS options and methods that can be used
      to return information about filtered, blocked, or censored DNS
      responses. It complements the information provided in EDNS
      Extended DNS Error options <xref target="RFC8914"/>.</t>

    </abstract>

  </front>
  <middle>

    <section anchor="sec_intro">

      <name>Introduction</name>

      <t>Some DNS nameservers return forged answers with different IP
      addresses when they filter, block, or censor access to an internet
      domain name. A service is typically setup to run at the forged
      address and return information about the filtering that was
      performed.</t>

      <t>This practice causes transport security-related errors at
      clients, such as the case where a HTTPS server serving at the
      forged answer's address does not have a valid TLS certificate
      configured for the domain name. A security error about a
      certificate mismatch is displayed by the web browser.</t>

      <t>This draft introduces EDNS options <xref target="RFC6891"/> for
      nameservers to provide more information to clients about the
      filtering as part of the DNS response itself, making the need to
      return forged answers unnecessary when domain names are
      filtered. By using these options instead of forged answers,
      security errors due to forged answers may be avoided at clients,
      and the information provided in these new EDNS options may be used
      to diagnose filtering or contact administrators of the DNS
      nameservers that performed filtering.</t>

    </section>

    <section>

      <name>Requirements notation</name>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
      "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
      described in <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
      when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown
      here.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec_ede_extra_text_language">

      <name>EDE-EXTRA-TEXT-LANGUAGE EDNS option</name>

      <t>This option specifies the language that is used in the
      EXTRA-TEXT field of EDNS Extended DNS Error options in the same
      DNS message. It is not limited to DNS filtering, but may be used
      in any DNS message that contains EDNS Extended DNS Error options.
      There MAY be zero or one EDE-EXTRA-TEXT-LANGUAGE EDNS option in a
      message.</t>

      <t>If a human-readable message is generated in the EXTRA-TEXT
      field of EDNS Extended DNS Error options, the nameserver MAY also
      include an EDE-EXTRA-TEXT-LANGUAGE EDNS option in the response. If
      the EDE-EXTRA-TEXT-LANGUAGE EDNS option is included, the language
      in its option data MUST match the language used in the EXTRA-TEXT
      field of the EDNS Extended DNS Error option.</t>

      <t>The EDNS OPTION-CODE of EDE-EXTRA-TEXT-LANGUAGE is provided in
      <xref target="sec_iana"/>. The OPTION-DATA MUST contain a language
      tag as described in <xref target="RFC5646" />.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec_filtering_contact">

      <name>FILTERING-CONTACT EDNS option</name>

      <t>When DNS queries cause filtering to be performed by nameservers
      and negative responses to be returned due to it, the nameserver
      MAY return zero or more FILTERING-CONTACT EDNS options in
      responses, containing contact information of the party that
      performed the filtering.</t>

      <t>DNS nameservers MAY generate these options as described
      in <xref target="sec_nameserver_behavior"/>. DNS clients MAY use
      the information in these options as described in <xref
      target="sec_client_behavior"/>.</t>

      <t>The EDNS OPTION-CODE of FILTERING-CONTACT is provided in <xref
      target="sec_iana"/>. The OPTION-DATA is a UTF-8 encoded string
      (that is not nul-terminated) containing a contact URI using a
      contact URI scheme listed in TBD: add a link to the contact URI
      scheme registry.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec_filtering_organization">

      <name>FILTERING-ORGANIZATION EDNS option</name>

      <t>When DNS queries cause filtering to be performed by nameservers
      and negative responses to be returned due to it, the nameserver
      MAY return zero or one FILTERING-ORGANIZATION EDNS option in
      responses, containing the name of the organization that performed
      the filtering.</t>

      <t>DNS nameservers MAY generate this option as described in <xref
      target="sec_nameserver_behavior"/>. DNS clients MAY use the
      information in this option as described in <xref
      target="sec_client_behavior"/>.</t>

      <t>The EDNS OPTION-CODE of FILTERING-ORGANIZATION is provided in
      <xref target="sec_iana"/>. The OPTION-DATA is a UTF-8 encoded
      string (that is not nul-terminated) containing the name of the
      organization that performed the filtering. The language used must
      match that specified in the EDE-EXTRA-TEXT-LANGUAGE EDNS option if
      the latter option is also included.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec_filtering_db">

      <name>FILTERING-DB EDNS option</name>

      <t>When DNS queries cause filtering to be performed by nameservers
      and negative responses to be returned due to it, the nameserver
      MAY return zero or one FILTERING-DB EDNS option in responses,
      containing the identifier, name, or description of the filtering
      database against which a matched query caused the filtering to
      occur.</t>

      <t>DNS nameservers MAY generate this option as described in <xref
      target="sec_nameserver_behavior"/>. DNS clients MAY use the
      information in this option as described in <xref
      target="sec_client_behavior"/>.</t>

      <t>The EDNS OPTION-CODE of FILTERING-DB is provided in <xref
      target="sec_iana"/>. The OPTION-DATA is a UTF-8 encoded string
      (that is not nul-terminated) containing the identifier, name, or
      description of the filtering database against which a matched
      query caused the filtering to occur.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec_nameserver_behavior">

      <name>DNS nameserver behavior</name>

      <t>When DNS nameservers filter/block/censor queries to domain
      names, it is RECOMMENDED that they do not return forged positive
      answers (e.g., containing a different IP address) to filtered
      queries, but instead return negative responses (NODATA or
      NXDOMAIN) containing an EDNS Extended DNS Error option <xref
      target="RFC8914" /> with corresponding INFO-CODE accurately
      indicating the kind of filtering that was performed.</t>

      <t>When such negative reponses are returned as a result of DNS
      filtering, DNS nameservers MAY include in DNS responses zero or
      more FILTERING-CONTACT EDNS options, and a FILTERING-ORGANIZATION
      EDNS option to provide information about the party that performed
      the filtering.</t>

      <t>The nameserver MAY return a human-readable message describing
      the filtering action that was performed in the EXTRA-TEXT field of
      the EDNS Extended DNS Error option. If a human-readable message is
      generated in the EXTRA-TEXT field, the nameserver MAY also include
      an EDE-EXTRA-TEXT-LANGUAGE EDNS option in the response.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec_client_behavior">

      <name>DNS client behavior</name>

      <t>DNS clients do not have to specify anything in their queries to
      nameservers to receive DNS filtering-related
      information. Nameservers would automatically return DNS
      filtering-related information in EDNS responses if they are setup
      to do so.</t>

      <t>When clients query DNS nameservers, they may receive DNS
      filtering-related information as part of the nameserver's
      responses. This information may be contained in the EDNS options
      described in this draft, as well as EDNS Extended DNS Error option
      fields (INFO-CODE and EXTRA-TEXT) <xref target="RFC8914" />.</t>

      <t>It is strongly RECOMMENDED that clients use DNS transport
      security protocols to query Privacy-enabling DNS servers as
      defined in <xref target="RFC9499" /> to protect the authenticity
      and integrity during transport of the DNS answer as well as the
      DNS filtering-related information that may be contained in it.</t>

      <t>DNS clients may receive zero or more FILTERING-CONTACT EDNS
      options in reponses. DNS clients MAY make use of the information
      in these options as they would like to. An example may be to
      display the contact information in a dialog message with
      hyperlinks, so that users may contact filtering parties.</t>

      <t>DNS clients may receive zero or more FILTERING-ORGANIZATION
      EDNS options in reponses. DNS clients MAY make use of the
      information in the first such EDNS option in the OPT RR as they
      would like to, and ignore any other FILTERING-ORGANIZATION
      options. An example may be to display the contact information in a
      dialog message with hyperlinks, so that users may contact
      filtering parties.</t>

    </section>

    <section>

      <name>Example DNS message</name>

      <t>The following is a sample packet dissection by Wireshark of a
      DNS response message containing the EDE-EXTRA-TEXT-LANGUAGE,
      FILTERING-CONTACT, FILTERING-ORGANIZATION, and FILTERING-DB EDNS
      options. This example was taken from the DNS responses generated
      in one of Loop's system tests. It was generated in response to RPZ
      processing <xref target="I-D.vixie-dnsop-dns-rpz" /> which
      returned an NXDOMAIN RCODE because the name being queried was
      blocked due to response policy.</t>

      <sourcecode>
Domain Name System (response)
    Transaction ID: 0x3172
    Flags: 0x8403 Standard query response, No such name
        1... .... .... .... = Response: Message is a response
        .000 0... .... .... = Opcode: Standard query (0)
        .... .1.. .... .... = Authoritative: Server is an authority
                              for domain
        .... ..0. .... .... = Truncated: Message is not truncated
        .... ...0 .... .... = Recursion desired: Don't do query
                              recursively
        .... .... 0... .... = Recursion available: Server can't do
                              recursive queries
        .... .... .0.. .... = Z: reserved (0)
        .... .... ..0. .... = Answer authenticated: Answer/authority
                              portion was not authenticated by the
                              server
        .... .... ...0 .... = Non-authenticated data: Unacceptable
        .... .... .... 0011 = Reply code: No such name (3)
    Questions: 1
    Answer RRs: 0
    Authority RRs: 0
    Additional RRs: 2
    Queries
        test1a.example.com: type A, class IN
            Name: test1a.example.com
            [Name Length: 18]
            [Label Count: 3]
            Type: A (1) (Host Address)
            Class: IN (0x0001)
    Additional records
        rpz1.example.com: type SOA, class IN, mname &lt;Root&gt;
            Name: rpz1.example.com
            Type: SOA (6) (Start Of a zone of Authority)
            Class: IN (0x0001)
            Time to live: 300 (5 minutes)
            Data length: 22
            Primary name server: &lt;Root&gt;
            Responsible authority's mailbox: &lt;Root&gt;
            [Responsible authority's mailbox name: &lt;Root&gt;]
            Serial Number: 1
            Refresh Interval: 600 (10 minutes)
            Retry Interval: 600 (10 minutes)
            Expire limit: 1200 (20 minutes)
            Minimum TTL: 600 (10 minutes)
        &lt;Root&gt;: type OPT
            Name: &lt;Root&gt;
            Type: OPT (41)
            UDP payload size: 4096
            Higher bits in extended RCODE: 0x00
            EDNS0 version: 0
            Z: 0x0000
                0... .... .... .... = DO bit: Cannot handle DNSSEC
                                      security RRs
                .000 0000 0000 0000 = Reserved: 0x0000
            Data length: 180
            Option: Extended DNS Error
                Option Code: Extended DNS Error (15)
                Option Length: 48
                Option Data: 000f5175657279206f7220616e737765722077
                             617320626c6f636b656420627920726573706f
                             6e736520706f6c696379
                Info Code: Blocked (15)
                Extra Text: Query or answer was blocked by response
                            policy
            Option: EDE-EXTRA-TEXT-LANGUAGE
                Option Code: EDE-EXTRA-TEXT-LANGUAGE (22)
                Option Length: 2
                Option Data: 656e
                Language: en
            Option: FILTERING-ORGANIZATION
                Option Code: FILTERING-ORGANIZATION (24)
                Option Length: 24
                Option Data: 546865204578616d706c65204f7267616e697a
                             6174696f6e
                Organization: The Example Organization
            Option: FILTERING-DB
                Option Code: FILTERING-DB (25)
                Option Length: 34
                Option Data: 476f7665726e6d656e7420416e74692d506972
                             61637920506f6c6963696573202331
                Database: Government Anti-Piracy Policies #1
            Option: FILTERING-CONTACT
                Option Code: FILTERING-CONTACT (23)
                Option Length: 26
                Option Data: 6d61696c746f3a737570706f7274406578616d
                             706c652e636f6d
                Contact: mailto:support@example.com
            Option: FILTERING-CONTACT
                Option Code: FILTERING-CONTACT (23)
                Option Length: 22
                Option Data: 736970733a68656c6c6f406578616d706c652e
                             636f6d
                Contact: sips:hello@example.com
      </sourcecode>

      <t>For completeness, here is a snippet from a Loop
      <tt>named.conf</tt> configuration file, that was used to configure
      the values returned in the filtering options in the response shown
      above:</t>

      <sourcecode>
options {
    // [snip...]

    edns-filtering-info-contacts {
        "mailto:support@example.com";
        "sips:hello@example.com";
    };

    edns-filtering-info-organization "The Example Organization";

    ede-extra-text-language "en";

    response-policy {
        // The default intent is blocking.
        zone "rpz1.example.com" filtering-db
            "Government Anti-Piracy Policies #1";
        zone "rpz2.example.com" intent blocking;
        zone "rpz3.example.com" intent censoring;
        zone "rpz4.example.com" intent filtering;
    } recursive-only no;

    // [snip...]
};
      </sourcecode>

    </section>

    <section>

      <name>Interoperability with Structured Error Data for Filtered DNS
      JSON</name>

      <t>When Structured Error Data for Filtered DNS JSON is explicitly
      requested by a DNS client by querying with the Structured DNS
      Error EDNS option as specified in Section <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-structured-dns-error" section="5.4"
      sectionFormat="bare">Structured DNS Error (SDE) EDNS(0) Option
      Format</xref> of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-structured-dns-error" />, a nameserver that
      also implements <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-structured-dns-error"
      /> MAY NOT return the EDE-EXTRA-TEXT-LANGUAGE, FILTERING-CONTACT,
      FILTERING-ORGANIZATION, and FILTERING-DB EDNS options in responses
      to such queries, and MAY instead process the query as specified in
      Section <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-structured-dns-error"
      section="5.2" sectionFormat="bare">Server Generating
      Response</xref> of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-structured-dns-error" />.</t>

      <t>A nameserver MUST NOT include the EDE-EXTRA-TEXT-LANGUAGE,
      FILTERING-CONTACT, FILTERING-ORGANIZATION, and FILTERING-DB EDNS
      options as well as Structured Error Data for Filtered DNS JSON in
      a single response. It must pick one, and the choice can be made
      based on whether the DNS client's query contained the Structured
      DNS Error option.</t>

    </section>

    <section>

      <name>Security considerations</name>

      <t>It is strongly RECOMMENDED that clients use DNS transport
      security protocols to query Privacy-enabling DNS servers as
      defined in <xref target="RFC9499"/> to protect the authenticity
      and integrity during transport of the DNS answer as well as the
      DNS filtering-related information that may be contained in it.</t>

      <t>TBD: Any other details that the dnsop WG and authors of
      draft-ietf-dnsop-structured-dns-error want to include.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec_iana">

      <name>IANA considerations</name>

      <t>IANA has allocated the following code points in the "DNS EDNS0
      Option Codes (OPT)" registry in the "Domain Name System (DNS)
      Parameters" registry group.</t>
      
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Value</th>
            <th>Name</th>
            <th>Status</th>
            <th>Reference</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>22</td>
            <td>EDE-EXTRA-TEXT-LANGUAGE</td>
            <td>Optional</td>
            <td>See <xref target="sec_ede_extra_text_language"/>.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>23</td>
            <td>FILTERING-CONTACT</td>
            <td>Optional</td>
            <td>See <xref target="sec_filtering_contact"/>.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>24</td>
            <td>FILTERING-ORGANIZATION</td>
            <td>Optional</td>
            <td>See <xref target="sec_filtering_organization"/>.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>25</td>
            <td>FILTERING-DB</td>
            <td>Optional</td>
            <td>See <xref target="sec_filtering_db"/>.</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec_acknowledgements">

      <name>Acknowledgements</name>

      <t>The FILTERING-CONTACT, FILTERING-ORGANIZATION, and
      EDE-EXTRA-TEXT-LANGUAGE EDNS options are based on the "c", "o",
      and "l" JSON fields respectively as listed in Section <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-structured-dns-error" section="4"
      sectionFormat="bare">I-JSON in EXTRA-TEXT Field</xref> of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-structured-dns-error" />.</t>

    </section>

  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative references</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5646.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6891.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8914.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9499.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative references</name>
        <xi:include href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/draft-ietf-dnsop-structured-dns-error-19.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/draft-vixie-dnsop-dns-rpz-00.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
